Ralph Wigum. Now, that is a name that I
never thought I would say on my YouTube
channel, but here we are. He's a
character from The Simpsons TV show and
apparently now the world's best software
engineer, and he is everywhere. You've
probably heard about the Bash Loops,
being able to run Claude Code for hours
and hours on end, completing entire
applications while you sleep. Like the
creator of Ralph Wigum here, completed a
$50,000 contract using it in less than
$300 of API credits for his coding
agent. Now, is this just a bunch of
hype? I mean, yes, it kind of is. And
that's what I want to cover with you
today because Ralph Wiggum is really the
final evolution of Vibe coding. And I
don't really mean that in a good way.
Now, there are some good takeaways from
Ralph Wigum as a framework and some
places that actually shine. So, we'll
cover that, but also get into where it
completely falls apart and what the real
solution is to push the boundaries of
what's possible with agent coding. We'll
get into agent harnesses. But to start
things off, let's get into what the heck
Ralph Wiggum actually is. So, in the
simplest terms possible, with Ralph
Wigum, we take our AI coding assistant
and we force it to run in a loop until
it has absolutely completed everything
for the feature request at hand. And so,
we have a prompt with our feature
request or the app we want to create. We
feed it into our coding agent like Cloud
Code. And then we have a hook. So, we're
going to detect when the agent is trying
to stop running and we're going to force
it to continue. Literally, we're going
to take the output from the agent and
feed it back into itself as the input
for the next run. And the only way that
it can exit this loop is by outputting a
safety phrase. Something like, "Hey, I'm
done. I've implemented absolutely
everything. Can I please exit the loop?"
And then finally, our hook will allow it
to pass control back to us. And so,
going back to the article I was showing
earlier, they have a simple oneliner to
explain it. We take our prompt, we feed
it into our coding agent, and we're just
running this in a while loop basically
forever or until we hit the end and we
have that safety phrase outputed that
we're looking for. And the beauty of
this, which I really do respect this,
even though I think there are a lot of
flaws to Ralph Wigum, is the technique
is deterministically bad in an
undeterministic world. And essentially
what that means is we're expecting the
coding agent to not do the best job. But
that's why we're allowing it to iterate
and iterate and iterate until finally it
accomplishes everything that it set out
to do. And this is very characteristic
of Ralph Wigum in The Simpsons.
Literally this character, the epitome of
Ralph Wigum is he always had these crazy
ideas that he did a very bad job with,
but he was so persistent that I guess
eventually he would succeed. And so
that's what we're doing here, forcing
our coding agent to take on that
persona. So, if you are interested in
trying Ralph Wiggum yourself, it's a
plugin that you can install into Cloud
Code in literally less than a minute.
I'll have a link to this in the
description, and I'll cover how we can
use this and exactly how it works in a
little bit. But I want to go back to the
diagram here and now draw the parallels
between Ralph Wigum and the essence of
vibe coding. I think you'll see very
quickly here why I'm saying Ralph Wiggum
is the epitome of vibe coding. So, when
vibe coding was coined at the start of
last year, there were a few phrases that
were used in Andre Karpathy's original
tweet. Basically, we're fully giving
into the vibes of our coding agent.
We're embracing exponentials. We're
forgetting the code even exists. We're
just talking in natural language to our
agent, describing what we want, and then
we're letting it do all of the work. So,
we're not doing any research. Generally,
you don't have any structured plan with
five coding. You trust the AI, and you
allow it to just iterate and iterate. So
whenever there's something that breaks,
you just say, "Hey Claude, this is not
working. Please go and fix it." You're
really not doing any critical thinking
yourself. You're just accepting whatever
comes out. And that really is Ralph
Wiggum because it's just vibe coding on
an infinite loop. We have the one
condition to break out of the loop. But
here we really are just iterating and
iterating countless times. And so the
philosophy here, which again I respect,
and I think there's something to be
taken away from this, is that
persistence beats sophistication. That
is the crux of Ralph Wiggum in the
Simpsons show. You try and try again and
eventually you succeed. And so looking
at how Vive coding has evolved, it
started as the gateway drug of just
basic prompts like okay, I'll trust my
coding agent to edit a single file. But
now, especially over the last year, we
started to trust our coding assistants
more and more. editing a ton of files at
once without checking its work, having
it build out entire features and just
going with the flow. And now it's gotten
to the point where we're building out
entire applications, literally forcing
our coding agent to run and run and run
until it says something is done. That's
Ralph Wigum. That's why I'm saying that
it's the peak of Vive coding, cuz it
literally can't get any more viby than
this. That is the ceiling of vibe coding
because we can't go beyond forcing our
coding agent to run until it finally
says the application is complete. And so
if the output of Ralph Wiggum is not
acceptable to us, we're at a dead end
here. If we want to vibe code, there's
nothing more that we can do. Finally, we
are forced to apply our own critical
thinking, put ourselves in the driver's
seat, and build a system. Heaven forbid
you have to build a system for your
coding agent. That's always what I am
the proponent of, which is why I'm not
really saying it's a good thing when
Ralph is the epitome of vibe coding.
Now, this whole idea of forcing our
agent to run for a very long time so it
can touch a lot of code and do a lot of
work. There are some use cases where
this is really powerful. So, I will talk
about this and then also generally when
it falls apart, which is most of the
time. But before we do this, I want to
actually show you Ralph Wigum in action,
how it works under the hood. So, like I
mentioned earlier, this is the official
Ralph Wigum Claude Code plugin. It is
the easiest way to bring Ralph Wiggum
into your coding environment. Now, you
can use this framework for other coding
assistants as long as they support
hooks, but almost everyone I know is
trying this out in Cloud Code
specifically. So, that's what I want to
show you. And so, in order to get this
installed, there's just a single command
that you have to run to bring the plugin
in. So, I'll have this in the
description as well. And so we're going
to install this from the in the official
Anthropic plug-in marketplace. I'll copy
this line. I'll go into my cloud code,
paste it in. This is the name of the
official plug-in marketplace from
Anthropic. And then the placeholder
here, I just have to replace with the
name of the Ralph plugin, which is
Ralph-loop.
And so I'll run this. It's going to say
that I already have it installed, but
for you, it'll bring it into your cloud
code for the first time. Couple
different options you have to select
there. And then you just have to restart
your cloud code. So I'll just show you
what that looks like here. I'm just
restarting the session to load in the
plugin. And now if I do /real, you can
see there are three options that I have
here. I have one to get help. This is
just going to give me a description of
how I use the plugin. Very nice. And
then we have one to start the loop,
which literally all we have to do here.
I'm going to press tab to complete. Is
we just have to specify the prompt, the
feature we want it to build. We can max
out the number of iterations if we want
to avoid burning all of our tokens. And
then the last thing we need to specify
is that safety phrase. What do we want
our coding agent to output to tell the
hook, hey, we are actually good to end
here. We have completed the
implementation. And then the last
command that we have here is the cancel
Ralph. And so if we want to just
abruptly end the loop just so we can get
out of that if it is just going way too
long, then we can run this manually. So
I'll show you a quick example of the
Ralph Wiggum loop right now. I'm not
going to run it live because the whole
point of this is that it goes for a
while, so it's pretty boring. But I'll
show you something after the fact just
so you have a good example. And so I use
the plugin here to run the Ralph loop. I
have a description for what I want it to
build. Just keeping it very simple here.
And then I'm allowing it to go forever.
I don't have max iterations. You
probably want to add that. And then I
have my completion promise. This is the
safety phrase as I keep calling it
jokingly. When it is absolutely sure
that it has accomplished the task set
out here, then it can output the word
done. And so if I go to the bottom of
the output here, we'll see that it did
that. It outputed done. And now it gave
me a summary. And then it passes the
control back to me. And so that's how I
know that the hook didn't force it to
continue because you can see my output
right here. And so going to the plug-in
folder here, I'll show you how this
works just a little bit under the hood.
It's pretty interesting. So if we go to
the hooks folder, we have a single hook
set up for cloud code. We are watching
for when cla code stops when it passes
control back to us. So we're going to
run a command when this happens. Now I
don't need to get into the code very
deeply for this obviously but
essentially we're just checking hey did
we reach the max iterations that we
specified we are allowing. If we did
then we'll end things short and we'll
also end things now if we have the
completion promise or in my case done is
the final output of our agent. So if
that's the case then we finish.
Otherwise, what we're going to do at the
very end here is take the output from
the previous agent, feed that in as the
input to the next run of Claude, forcing
it to continue in a loop. And the way
that we know what iteration we're on is
also as a part of Ralph Wiggum, we have
this local file where we're basically
just keeping track of the state for the
loop. So, we have my request here, what
I wanted to build, the fact that it's
active. We did two iterations. This is
our completion promise. And so this is
essentially the file that drives the
entire loop. So Ralph Wiggum is really
simple overall. It's just this file with
some prompting to explain how to use it
and then the stop hook. There is nothing
more to it. It's actually beautifully
simple. The sponsor of today's video is
Dev Stats, which is essentially a
cockpit dashboard for engineering teams.
And so if you are running a team or you
just want to see where your dev time is
actually going, this is a tool that will
change how you operate, especially if
you're relying on coding agents. And so
all you have to do is connect your
GitHub or GitLab repositories. And then
you can instantly visualize the entire
software development life cycle and
going to the integrations here. Not only
can you connect your repositories, but
you can also connect your task
management software like Jira or Linear.
So, in order to show you the true power
of Devstats, I have a repo connected
here for a fictitious project. This is a
nod to the TV series, A Silicon Valley.
And so, I just want to show you how much
we can really glean as far as insights
from devstats. And so, even on the
homepage right here, we already have so
much information. We can see the average
time that it takes for every step of the
way in the software development life
cycle. And we can click into all of our
individual team members to see their
contributions and deliverables. and even
seeing how much you're doing per
activity type, like pull requests and
code reviews. We also can go into the PR
cycle time, so we can see on average how
long it takes to go from issue all the
way to deployment. We can look at aging
branches and issues to see what's going
stagnant that maybe we should address on
priority. We even have the Dora metrics,
so being able to see things like sprint
accuracy, our change failure rate, how
quickly we recover from those things,
the kinds of things that leadership
really cares about. And this is just
scratching the surface for the insights
and data that's available on the
platform. So if you want to ship faster
and actually know what is slowing you
down, regardless of if you're working
with a big team or just using your
coding agents, then it's definitely
worth checking out. I'll have a link to
them in the description. So I have to
hand it to Ralph Wigum. There are a lot
of use cases where having this simple
harness just with some prompting and a
hook to force it to go for a long time
is very useful. So generally the kinds
of tasks that have a super clear
completion criteria and are
fundamentally easy to accomplish. It's
just you have to touch a lot of code and
spend a lot of time in the codebase. So
things like migrations, refactors, and
adding better test coverage to your
codebase. Ralph Wiggum is great for
this. The goal is very unambiguous and
doesn't require a lot of human judgment.
Now that is if you have a lot of
validation in place, which with Ralph
Wingham by default, you really don't.
That's another problem that I'll talk
about in a little bit. But the main
problem with Ralph Wigum is it really
falls apart for any kind of
judgmentheavy task, especially when you
have ambiguous completion criteria. You
need more creative freedom to really
establish when a task is complete. And
so, a few problems with Ralph Wake. The
first thing is that without a lot of
direction, agents love to overengineer.
If you've done any kind of vibe coding
yourself and they looked at the results
after, the mess you have to clean up is
generally because the coding agent is
doing way more than it really needs to
for the feature implementation. And so
overbaking is another phrase for this.
It happens all the time with Ralph
Wigum. And also not having human in the
loop, especially when you're doing very
longunning tasks, is pretty scary and
dangerous because a lot of times you
have to do course correction. I have
this happen all the time where I do a
feature implementation with my coding
agent and it doesn't do a good job. And
so I look into what it created. I work
with the coding assistant to address the
issue whether it be overengineering or
just poorly written code, whatever it
is. And then I make sure that that
doesn't happen again. With Ralph Loop,
we don't have the luxury to do that
because we aren't stepping in after each
step of the way. We're just letting it
go, go, go. And that's so dangerous,
especially because of the rabbit holes
that we can get stuck in as well. coding
agents will get into these failure loops
where they encounter an issue while
they're validating. They try to fix it,
but they fail over and over and over
again because they just fundamentally
misunderstand the problem. And so,
you're burning thousands, hundreds of
thousands, millions of tokens trying to
address something. And so, yeah, with
the max iterations, we can prevent it
from going forever and ever, but then
we're still not getting the output that
we want. Now, I know this sounds very
doom and gloom, but there are some
solutions, things we can combine with
Ralph Wiggum to make it more structured
and reliable. The first idea is
combining the PRP framework with Ralph
Wigum. I've covered this a lot on my
channel before. I'll link to a video
right here, but PRP or the product
requirement prompt is a process for
creating a structured plan of attack for
a feature implementation with your
coding agent before you send the task
off and have it knock everything out.
And this is so important for Ralph Wigum
because it assumes that you have a good
prompt. And that, my friend, is a
terrible assumption because creating a
good structured plan is probably the
most difficult part for working with
coding agents in the first place. And so
when we don't have a process defined to
do that, then we really are just vibe
coding. And so we're stepping away from
vibe coding, when we start to use
something like PRP to do research,
requirement gathering, building the
blueprint with the coding agent. So we
really have a well-curated set of
context to then feed into the Ralph loop
to knock things out in all of the loops
that we are stringing together. And so
in our plan, this is where we can define
the success criteria. So the agent is
truly accurate when it outputs that
phrase at the end saying that it's done.
Because that's another problem with
Ralph is even though the whole point of
it is that it only says it's done when
it truly is, we still encounter that
classic problem with the coding agent
where sometimes it'll say it's done when
there's still things that are missing
what we asked it to do. And so the PRP
framework, again, I will link to this in
the description. Raasmus the creator of
PRP he added Ralph Wigum directly into
the PRP framework and the plugin that we
can install in a very similar way to the
official one. So we have the PRP Ralph
and the PRP Ralph cancel. So similar
commands but now the point of this is
that the input to PRP Ralph instead of
it just being a basic prompt we're going
to input a PRP where we have that very
structured plan. And so I'll give you a
quick example of this right now. So
first we have to install a marketplace
and plugin for PRP which I'll have these
commands in description as well. So we
just add Rasmus' marketplace and uh it's
going to clone it. Takes a little bit to
install and then after that which I
already have installed which is why I
get this error. Then we can specifically
install PRP core which comes with the
Ralph Wiggum edition. And so I'll show
you a brief conversation here. when we
start our planning process, we just want
to have a conversation with our coding
agent understanding what we want to
build or what we want to add next into
our codebase. And so I have that
conversation. I establish the criteria
with the coding agent and then I'm going
to invoke the process here to start the
creation of the PRP. So I run the
command that comes with the plug-in and
I just say like, hey, based on our
conversation, let's create the full plan
for the data persistence layer. So we
create this artifact here. If I go into
the PRPS folder, we can see in the plans
here, I've got this one. It's already
completed because I did this ahead of
time, but this is our structured plan.
It's a lot of context here around the
criteria, the task list, our validation
strategy, what we want our codebase to
look like after. This is now our input
into the Ralph loop. It is much much
better than the first example that I
gave you here, which where it was just a
single sentence. And so now we start a
brand new conversation and we do the PRP
Ralph command. And then our parameter
here is just the path to our structure
plan. So it still uses Ralph Wigam in
exactly the same way. We're going and
going and going until it's done, but now
we have much better context. This leads
to insanely better results. Like you
have no idea how much better it is using
PRP Ralph versus just the regular Ralph
Wigum sending in a super simple request.
Okay, so this is all fine and dandy and
PRP plus Ralph Wigum is a powerful
combo, but if you've really been paying
attention to the problems that I've laid
out here for Ralph Wiggum, then you'll
know that this is not enough. This
doesn't solve all our problems. It does
help us with our planning and success
criteria, but we still have no course
correction, and we still risk our agent
going down these rabbit holes because in
the end, Ralph is still dictating the
entire process. It's only the planning
that we're putting ourselves in the
driver's seat up front. And so what we
really need to make something like Ralph
Wiggum actually work and be a lot more
than Vive coding is an agent harness.
And so I've covered agent harnesses a
good amount on my channel already. I'll
link to a video right here specifically
with one that Enthropic has built for
us. And so the whole point of an agent
harness is it is the infrastructure
wrapping around the model for longunning
tasks to add in reliability and things
like human in the loop. And so Ralph
Wiggum is essentially the most basic
harness we can possibly have. It's a
hook and some prompting. Definitely not
enough, but it shows us the very
beginning of what is possible. Now to
have a agent harness that actually works
for creating production ready code
avoiding all of these problems there's a
lot that we need and really I think the
whole industry is just starting to get
into what makes an effective harness
usually you have a sort of initializer
agent to set the stage for the project
as you're going through all these loops
structured progress tracking which we
really don't have with Ralph Wigum at
all of course human in the loop error
recovery memory compression and being
able to have better handoff between the
different sessions as we're running them
in the loop. We don't have that with
Ralph at all either. And then more of an
actual validation strategy built in.
Now, this is partially solved with
having PRP plus Ralph Wiggum, but
actually making it like
deterministically a part of the process.
Not to get too in the weeds right now,
but like that is like so so important.
And so I think that Ralph Wigum really
is the Model T of AI coding, right? Like
it's not the Tesla. It's still vibe
coding. It's not going to take you far,
but it shows what the real skill is
going to be for this year. Agent
harnesses with proper human in the loop.
A problem that is far from solved right
now. And something that I'm going to be
diving headirst into this year. I'm
going to be doing live streaming
content, a lot of work behind the scenes
to build these sorts of harnesses and
share it with you. I want to create an
optimal harness. And so, I'm throwing
myself into a lot of research right now,
seeing what it really takes. And so I
know that like some of what I'm
presenting right now might be a little
vag to you cuz I'm still figuring it out
for myself, but yes, 2026 the
competitive advantage is going to shift
from the model. It's not going to be
hype about all these new LLMs. Instead,
it's going to be the harness, the
rappers, the tooling that we are
building around the LLMs that will make
AI coding more and more reliable and
keeping us in the driver's seat while
still allowing the agent to handle
longer and longer running tasks. So, if
that sounds good to you and you really
want to stay on the cutting edge of a
coding, I would really appreciate a like
and a subscribe. A lot more content on
agent harnesses coming very soon. And
that, my friend, is all I have for you
right now. I hope that you have a lovely
rest of your day and I will see you in
the next